# Sven Van Bael

#### **PERSONAL DETAILS**

vanbaels.github.io

# **PROFILE**

I'm a former (post)doctoral researcher with an interest in data analysis and visualisation.

My expertise lies in interpreting large multidimensional datasets using the R programming language, RStudio and Quarto. Using statistical methods, I can transform raw values into valuable insights and conclusions.

I enjoy the challenge of creating clean, comprehensible, and impactful data visualizations, facilitating the communication of results to various audiences (specialists, colleagues, students, and the broader public)

#### **RELEVANT SKILLS**

- Analysis of relatively large multidimensional datasets.
- Experience with the R programming language and associated packages for data importing (readr, readxl), structuring (tibble, tidyr, forcats), processing (dplyr, magrittr), and visualization (ggplot2).
- Knowledge of linear statistic models for hypothesis testing.
- String pattern recognition using regular expressions and the R package stringr.
- Experience with Quarto for creating reports and websites.
- Familiar with Shiny and PowerBI for developing interactive dashboards.

## **LANGUAGES**

DUTCH (mother tongue)

Speaking
Reading
Writing

WROUND

WROU

Speaking Reading Writing

GERMAN

Speaking Reading Writing

**FRENCH** 

Speaking Reading Writing

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Post-doctoral researcher – University of Antwerp

Nov. 2020 - Oct. 2023

Centre for Proteomics

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Geert Baggerman

My research interests involved the potential alternative processing of neuropeptides by proprotein convertases and optimising a timsTOF Pro instrument to detect these low-abundant alternative neuropeptides.

#### Post-doctoral researcher – KU Leuven

Jan. 2019 - Oct. 2023

Research group of Molecular and Functional Neurobiology Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Liesbet Temmerman

In this research, I developed DDA/PRM/DIA methods for the detection of endogenous peptides with an orbitrap instrument.

# Short research stay at Technische Universität München (DE)

Nov. 2019 and Jul. 2020

Bavarian Center for Biomolecular Mass Spectrometry Supervisor: Dr. Christina Ludwig

#### PhD research - KU Leuven

Oct. 2014 - Dec. 2018

Research group of Functional Genomics and Proteomics Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Liliane Schoofs

Dissertation: Neuropeptidomics in C. elegans

## **EDUCATION**

## PhD in Biochemistry - KU Leuven

2014 - 2018

#### Master in Biochemistry and Biotechnology – KU Leuven

2012 - 2014 (Magna cum laude)

Thesis: Metformin-mediated longevity in Caenorhabditis elegans

Academic Bachelor in Biochemistry and Biotechnology – KU Leuven 2011-2012

Professional Bachelor Pharmaceutical and Biological Laboratory Technology – University College Leuven

2007 - 2011

#### **FIVE SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

(For a complete record of publications, visit ORCID.org/0000-0002-6948-1020)

**Van Bael S**, Ludwig C, Baggerman G, Temmerman L (2024). Identification and targeted quantification of endogenous neuropeptides in the nematode *Caenorhabditis elegans* using mass spectrometry. In: Schrader M, Fricker L (eds) *Peptidomics. Methods in Molecular Biology*.

Cockx B\*, **Van Bael S\***, Boelen R, Vandewyer E, Ludwig C, Dalzell JJ, Yang H, Lee J, Beets I, Temmerman L (2023). Mass spectrometry-driven discovery of neuropeptides mediating nictation behavior of nematodes. *Molecular & Cellular Proteomics*.

Preza M, **Van Bael S**, Temmerman L, Guarnaschelli I, Castillo E, Koziol U (2022). Global analysis of neuropeptides in cestodes identifies Attachin, a SIFamide homolog, as a stimulant of parasite motility and attachment. *Journal of Neurochemistry*.

**Van Bael S**, Watteyne J, Boonen K, De Haes W, Menschaert G, Ringstad N, Horvitz HR, Schoofs L, Husson SJ, Temmerman L (2018). Mass spectrometric evidence for neuropeptide-amidating enzymes in Caenorhabditis elegans. Journal of Biological Chemistry.

**Van Bael S**, Zels S, Boonen K, Beets I, Schoofs L, Temmerman L (2018). A Caenorhabditis elegans Mass Spectrometric Resource for Neuropeptidomics. *Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry*.

\*Authors contributed equally to this work

#### INVITED SPEAKER PRESENTATIONS

Quantitative Neuropeptidomics in C. *elegans*. Invited presentation at the Belgian Proteomics Association conference, Liège, **Belgium**, 5 May **2022**.

Targeted Neuropeptidomics in C. elegans. Invited speaker op de BayBioMS Advanced MS seminar (21 Oct. **2020**). **Germany**, available online (YouTube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3QzleffNVHo">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3QzleffNVHo</a>).

Targeted Neuropeptidomics in *C. elegans*. Invited presentation at the EPIC-XS annual consortium member meeting, Davos, **Switzerland**, 29 Jan – 31 Jan **2020**.

Characterization of Neuropeptide-amidating Enzymes in Caenorhabditis elegans by Mass Spectrometry. Competitive selection of abstract, presented at the 29th ASMS Sanibel Conference on Mass Spectrometry, Clearwater (FL), **USA**, 19 Jan – 22 Jan **2017**.

#### **COMPETITIVELY OBTAINED GRANTS**

# European Proteomics Infrastructure Consortium providing access (EPIC-XS) 2019

I was selected for EPIC-XS, a Horizon 2020-funded program providing access to researchers at an international proteomics facility within the European Union. I used this opportunity to develop a targeted neuropeptidomics method for C. elegans, in collaboration with Dr. Christina Ludwig at TU München.

#### Junior postdoctoral fellowship FWO Flanders

Jun. 2020 – Fonds Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek Vlaanderen (FWO Flanders)

Postdoctoral fellowship (three-year period). The success rate that year was 25.7%.

# Postdoctoral mandate (PDM)

Jan. 2019 – KU Leuven

Postdoctoral grant (one-year period) for supporting young researchers that apply for a long-term postdoctoral position with an external finance institution. The success rate that year was 35%.

#### **Fellowship IWT Flanders**

Jan. 2015 – Agency for Innovation by Science and Technology in Flanders (IWT Flanders)

PhD doctoral grant for strategic fundamental research (four-year period). The success rate that year was 26.5%.